You're listening to TIP. You're listening to The Richer. Why isn't Happier podcast? Where your host, William Green, interviews the world's greatest investors and explores how to win in markets and life. This show is not investment advice, it's intended for informational and entertainment purposes only. All opinions expressed by hosts and guests are solely their own, and they may have investments in the securities discussed. Now for your host, William Green.
Hi there, this is William Green, host of the Richer Wyser Happier podcast. Before I welcome today's very special guest, I wanted to share some news that I'm really excited about. Later this year, I'll launch a new Richer Wyser Happier masterclass for a small, very intimate group of 22 people who'd like to study with me over the course of a year. We'll meet once a month over Zoom to discuss the most important themes in my book, Richer Wyser Happier,
And I'll also talk about how my thinking on these subjects continues to evolve, drawing on lessons from hundreds of hours of interviews that I've conducted with many of the world's greatest investors. Members of the Masterclass group will also be invited to join me at two unique in-person events, starting with a two-day gathering in New York later this fall. My goal in forming the Masterclass is to create a year-long journey of exploration
for people who are deeply interested in building lives that are truly richer, wiser and happier. If this idea appeals to you, please email my friend and fellow podcast host Kyle Grieve, who's in charge of the waitlist, and he can share details with you about prices and dates and the like. His email address is kyle.com. I should also mention this will be the third year in a row that I've hosted a richer, wiser, happier masterclass.
The first two groups included an amazingly accomplished selection of people from many countries around the world, including some hugely successful hedge fund and mutual fund managers, various asset allocators, wealth advisors, managers of family offices, a management consultant, a doctor, several CEOs and entrepreneurs, and a renowned physicist turned quant fund manager. Part of the beauty of the masterclass lies in the very strong relationships forged between its members.
many of whom have become really good friends. If you like the idea of studying with me and this extraordinary group of keen investors and passionate learners, please email Kyle at theinvestorspodcast.com. And if the stars align, I'd love to see you later this year when the masterclass begins. Thanks so much. And now on with the show. Hi, folks. We have a very special treat for you today. I'm really excited to welcome back a terrific hedge fund manager who's one of the most thoughtful people in the investment world.
And one of my favorite people in the investment world too. His name is Chris Begg and he's the CEO and the CIO, the Chief Investment Officer of East Coast Asset Management. Chris teaches the security analysis class at Columbia Business School that Ben Graham famously taught back in the early 1950s when his star student was Warren Buffett. He's also a dear friend, so I'm particularly thrilled to have him back on the podcast. It's wonderful to see you, Chris. William, it's great to be here as always. Thank you.
And I was just explaining to you before we started that part of my challenge today. It's that you gave me so much to read of your unpublished essays and the like that I ended up this morning with 42 pages of notes and questions that I put together while preparing for this interview. I counted it was almost 20,000 words. So there's this sort of perennial challenge of synthesis and distillation. I got it down to about 13 pages this morning. So if I'm confused, you'll know why.
So I spent the last few days reading a lot of your unpublished essays and I think our last count you'd written something like 46 of them. I've read probably a couple of handfuls. I've listened to dozens of the 150 songs or more that you've written in the last couple of years. I've reread your last year's year-end that is shelled as it was 30 pages plus an addendum, an unpublished addendum that was another 11 pages. And so as I was working my way through this, I was like,
Oh my god, my friend Chris, he's actually a much more prolific writer than I am. And I started to realize, oh, this is really central to your process, the process of writing. And it's so key to you in terms of building your philosophy of investing, business and life. And so I wanted to start actually by asking you about the process of writing for you and why it's so important as part of this broader challenge that you have and that I have, which you describe as
compressing complexity into essence. That's right. Wow. What a great intro, William. Thank you. Yeah, the writing for me, when we launched the firm in 2008, there was a lot I had to say because I had to articulate the process. And so I started writing quarterly letters. And the quarterly letters were so helpful to me as I was kind of working through getting that process articulated on paper. And that moved to
annual letters. There wasn't as much to say quarterly, plus there was a lot of work getting those quarterly letters up. And the annual letter became another way to compress how the philosophy of it was evolving, holdings and so forth. I still look back at those at that period of time as probably the most important period of learning that I've had. And so having a methodology to take this learning and to put it into words and then
with the idea that there's an audience that might read this. So there's a bar of excellence that you're looking for, a quality that you want versus it just being in my journal, the learnings being in the journal and so forth. And a couple of years ago, I paused some of the year-end letter writing as well. And it was a couple of years where I didn't have an outlet for some of the learning I was doing. And so when I came back to it, which you referred to the year-end letter last year, it kind of opened up something in me.
that had been kind of held back and so now like you said this period of time which is the last 12 months or so has been probably the most prolific writing I've done in my career. And these essays that have emerged from the learning they've been fun to write and I continue to get a lot of satisfaction from the process so. Your next question at some point is going to be what are you going to do with them how are you going to publish them and after your dinner in Omaha.
I was walking with Eric Markowitz, who's writing a beautiful book called Outlast about things that endure through time. And I shared with him about some of these essays that were coming out and I was calling them essays at the time. And he was the first person to have said to me, he's like, wait a sec, Chris, if at the time was about 15 to 18 of these 3000 words a piece. He said, so let me get this straight, you've written a book. So maybe it's on its way to something that looks like a book, but we'll see.
Yeah, that would be great and Eric is working on something really important and will definitely I hope come on the podcast when it's published in several months and it's very similar in a sense that both of you are looking. What in duos what outstanding businesses endure for example and so, yeah, we'll discuss that topic further as we go along one thing that struck me. Is that even though you're very prolific with your writing you're really not in a hurry and.
When you did come out with that year-end letter at the end of 2025, which we'll discuss a lot in this discussion because it really gets at some very profound ideas, I think, about investing in life. When you published it, you pointed out that actually it was two or three years since you'd published your previous annual letter, which is kind of interesting and unusual. And you wrote, over the last two years, I found that every time I sat down to write what I thought would be the next letter, the ideas were still becoming. And you said certain ideas
need to be lived longer before they can be written honestly. And you like me are somewhat obsessed with Robert Persegg and Zen and the Automotive Cycle Maintenance. And I kept thinking about this line that he wrote that I don't know if you remember that I think I quoted in the notes on sources and resources in my book where he said, as he was setting about writing his book, he said, I don't want to hurry it. That itself is a poisonous 20th century attitude when you want to hurry something.
that means you no longer care about it and want to get on to other things. I just want to get at it slowly, but carefully and thoroughly. And I wondered what sorts that stirred in you. Oh, I love that. Yeah. And as you know, Perseg is probably my favorite, one of my favorite authors. Definitely two of the best in my top 10 books are Zen and Lila. So, yeah, I feel those, the year-end letters are a reflection on
this craft that we've taken on and they should be approached with a sense of mastery. And during that time period, I was working through something I thought was very, very important that I thought could be compressed to a year-end letter. And when I realized it struggled to be... It couldn't fit into the year-end letter format. And I had to let go of a little bit of what that topic was.
and allow it to come out in different other forms. And that was okay. So coming back and writing this year-end letter, distilling pieces of what I had been working on was a relief in a way because I had to release a little bit of what I wanted to say in its full form. So as you know, what we've tried to do at East Coast is a little non-conforming. We're trying to compound capital at very high rates of return over a long period of time.
And we've self-selected for bringing partners, friends along with us. We're not thinking ourselves in the business to build a big investment management company. That's never been part of our objective. It's to really think about excellence and quality. So our partners, if we miss a year-end letter because we're working on something, I think they're quite forgiving. And they understood that the process has not paused at all.
And I should probably mention I am a partner in the fund so I was quite happy with Chris's silence. I'm like, good, he's working on something that may enable me to retire before the age of 135. I thought part of what was interesting though, you know, one of your essays is about what you call the consecration of attention. And so this idea of going slowly and living really thoughtfully with important subjects.
This is more than a passing interest of yours and it's obviously a huge timely issue and challenge at the moment. And you wrote in that essay about how we're all living in this environment that trains people to seek interruption, to prefer novelty to continuity, to confuse the constant movement of information with the actual deepening of understanding. And you talked about the challenge of this bottleneck of attention as you put it.
information floods towards us, summaries multiply, opinions crowd every surface. Almost anything can be sampled instantly. A person can live in the illusion of omnidirectional learning while scarcely having entered anything deeply enough to be changed by it. And so I'm really curious because I'm so faced with this issue, right? I'm constantly bombarded with podcasts and books and articles and sub-stack pieces and everything seems kind of worthwhile or marginally worthwhile.
And I'm wondering how in the midst of this kind of bombardment of information, of this illusion of omnidirectional learning as you put it, how have you managed to train your attention and develop what you call the will to remain with a topic until you reach hard one simplicity? Yeah, this was something that I think early in my career, I realized I had much more of that right brain creative
But also the willingness to kind of go broad. I think in the early days, if I were to critique my process, I was maybe a couple inches deep in a mile wide. I wanted to know a lot about physics, biology, all the bio, you know, you wanted to just have the information. But when tested, I realized I didn't have a first principle understanding of that, of that topic at a level that that I was, you know, I could, I could pass as being
you know, knowledgeable about it. But it wasn't the level that I wanted to be knowledgeable about it. So I set out a goal as we've talked about in the past where, you know, I would spend these three month periods of time going very, very deep, that consecration of attention to train myself to really understand something from the foundation up. And that habit clicked because I really, really enjoyed it. And I realized when I did that, I was starting to connect one field to the next.
and I had a place to store the information in my mind so I could access it. It had a longer shelf life when I was doing this. It wasn't like in and out. So I guess it created a bit of a flywheel, a reflexivity. Once I saw it working, then I continued to hone the habit. And to this day, that process definitely lives in the portfolio. We run a long only concentrate portfolio so we can get to know these companies really, really well.
And it feels like we're going on a journey with them that in the early stages, we expected to last decades. So we can go unhurried. We can have this deep understanding, this deep relationship with the information. And I feel like all these subjects that that I work on, they are not subjects, they're almost embodied learnings that become part of you. You know, and that's why I wrap them in art and poetry and other things because
Each one of those mediums have a different connection to the material. And that's what's fun about these essays is that it's a way to take some of these personal portals and find the underlying law that is a general principle that can be observed through this portal. Yeah. And I think part of why I wanted to stop by discussing this subject is I wanted to make it clear to our listeners.
and our viewers that in a way this isn't just about investing, it's about a different way of carrying yourself in the world where there's so much pressure to be quick and shallow and scattered. And one of the things that makes I think your approach worthy of study is the fact that it's so counter cultural. And there's a line that I thought I would quote from that essay on the consecration of attention that I really love where you said, everywhere I found anything worthy.
I have found the same hidden law beneath it. Stay longer, go closer, return again, refuse premature summary, hold the light steady, let the thing teach you how it must be seen. And that clearly has huge ramifications for investing, as we'll see, because a lot of what we're discussing is looking at companies that are temporarily obscured by misperception. Can you talk about that idea of
just as a general sort of operating principle, staying longer, going closer, returning again, refusing premature summary. Yeah. You know, when we think about the normal tendency that we all have as humans is a system one instinct of survival and distinction. You know, there's this... Those are the things that are working on us at all times. And
As we get bombarded with this information, short-term information, you're feeling, ah, this is fearful or I want to do more of this because I'm seeing others winning by doing more of this. And so that's the temptation, certainly in investing, is that you're constantly being bombarded by short-term news that's giving you a sense of fear or greed or fear or missing out. And so trying to quiet those natural instincts.
so that you can reason through something, you know, what Conerman talks about system two, and then moving beyond system two where it becomes embodied, right? That when you see the short-term news, you can you quiet it naturally and that you're being guided by an intuition that feels natural. And I think that connects to what you said is this, it just becomes a habit of doing it more and more where you can actually
feel into these moments where, okay, I feel system one gearing up around these things, but I know the the quieting of that. I know what it feels like to quiet it. I know what it feels like to reason through and I know what it feels like to to have an intuition or insight that guides me into something that maybe is more intelligent. Do you have recommendations when you're teaching your students, for example, or analysts at your fund and your
trying to encourage them to build a life that fosters that kind of spaciousness and ability to think and go deep. What do you actually encourage people to do in terms of their habits from meditation to sleep to breathing, whatever it is. And in your case, I think part of it is that you spend half the year living basically in the jungle, not in such a rustic way, but physically very removed from the noise. Yeah.
I was thinking about that this morning, William. Would Warren Buffett be the investor that he became if he lived in Manhattan? Can you picture Warren living in Manhattan and having the track record that he had? There was a sense of that removal from maybe what felt very hard to do something that was more long-term oriented. I think geography is really important. I see a lot of MBA students
probably over a thousand now that come to me usually in their second year at Columbia Business School. And they're exceptional, right? Of course they're exceptional. They're there. But the speed with which that they're in a hurry to get back into the workforce, to get back into making money, paying off student loans, whatever it might be, it's hard to slow them down. It really is. And they're seeing what their friends are doing. They're interviewing. They're getting a job at an investment bank.
and they have to take the interview, but I get to a handful of them and they leave our course or our time together and they're saying, ah, I'm seeing things differently. I'm going to do this. I'm going to take this track. I'm going to work for a business and learn how to operate a business. And I love that. It's not that I'm trying to... I don't have any philosophy of the way to do it, but some listen and change track. I love working with undergrads for that purpose because
They're a little bit more removed from it. They're a little bit more of a blank canvas and you can kind of share with them some of these things that may lead to them having more spaciousness for a career that might align more with their temperament. I was very struck. I went on a meditation retreat a few times with Sokni Rinpoche, who's been a guest on the podcast with Daniel Goldman, the writer of Emotional Intelligence, who's also a great meditation expert and practitioner.
And when I went to New York the first couple of days I would say, Sokni had all of these practices to get the New Yorkers like me to settle their nervous energy. And you know, there's a beautiful Tibetan Buddhist word where he would talk about lung, which I think means this kind of speedy, buzzy energy that's up in your head, which I have the whole time, or at least much of the time. And then I went and did a meditation retreat with my son, Henry, a six day meditation retreat with Sokni Ravchay in England in the countryside in England.
And that process that took about two days in New York took about five minutes in England like they were so much less busy and frenetic and it was I had this image it sounds like a negative image but it's really not of them as like cows chomping in the field like it was just so much easier for them to settle. And so I think that's one of the big challenges that we have it's like you know you need to be pretty dynamic to do well in the world and to compete and yet at the same time you need this kind of.
this chill, spacious, calm, quiet ability to step back and see truth, I think. Yeah, we've had this multi-geography life now for about seven years and two different latitudes. And it was a bit of work for the family to kind of re-architect. COVID was a little bit of our permission to at least experiment with this. And it's, I think, from an investment standpoint,
it's really, really been kind of transformational in the sense of opening up a different lens, a different calibration of time. And I think connecting with nature is something that I continue to see just enormous benefits from, whether it's surfing or going for a long walk and thinking. All of those things, I think, are really important to think through something that's really important.
You know, we're working through investment decisions. I was even reading about Nikola Tesla when he came up with his most insightful idea. It was like literally he's on the banks of a river quoting Gerta. You know, he was like listening to his like reciting poetry and it clicked. You know, so I think removing yourself and being in a place where you can think independently is extremely valuable. I want to talk in some depth about
year-end letter from 2025 because I think it gets at some really, really important points about how to invest and think and businesses, how to live. As part of my preparation for this conversation, I was looking back at our old text messages because we texted each other pretty often. You had sent me a draft of your year-end letter back in January before you published it. I wrote back to you. I just finished reading your extraordinarily rich shareholder letter.
It's a lovely letter exceptionally thoughtful full of intellectual riches soulful and beautifully written. I'm not sure that I can think of anyone other than Warren Buffett and Nick Sleep who has written shareholder letters of this quality. And then I said I read the final section to my wife Lauren just now and then said he can really write and I said as she knows that's very very rare praise from me and so.
Yeah, really struck me this letter. And so I went back this week and spent a couple of days with it because it's long. And then there was this unpublished addendum that you'd written since then, which I would say read. And the letter gets at this really important overarching theme. It's all about things that are hiding in plain sight. Can you talk about that theme and about how you relate it to this pirate ship, a treasure ship from your childhood? Yeah. Thank you, William.
by the way, when I sent you an early copy of the letter, that was the most unsettling, the waiting process if William would approve of this letter. When you sent that back, it was very kind because I felt like it was close to a final draft at that point. The hiding in plain sight, I always like to find a personal portal to a law. And so I was thinking back to what really, really got me excited about research.
and research as a craft. And I reflected back to my, it was my senior year in high school. And I had probably the, my favorite teacher of all time, Mick Carlin. And he was the journalist teacher at Barnsville High School on the Cape where I was, where I went to high school. And he was one of these just real exceptional teachers. And if your work, your research work, your journalism was good enough, you got published in the school newspaper. So at the time, my father's best friend, Barry Clifford,
Bessram from Growing Up had discovered the only recovered pirate ship about in 1984, so years earlier. And it'd been kind of the part of the family, right? Like listening to the stories of this pirate ship. And of course, as a young boy, there's nothing of a better story than a found pirate ship. And he found it right off the well fleet. It was literally not far from where we kind of grew up surfing.
and to think that this treasure was under the water, hiding in plain sight. So I wrote about it for that paper and was published in the school newspaper, but it stayed with me. And so the letter was kind of a reflection on that history. My love really started my love of research and to realize that if you worked with something long enough with the research, you can actually arrive at an insight or a treasure in the case of what Barry found.
And I find that that's kind of what we do every day, if we're really kind of looking across this wide field of investment opportunities to try to understand what is being, what's hiding there? What is that exceptional business that for some reason is being ignored and therefore the valuation gives us an opportunity to earn
above market returns over a long period of time. So that's really the element of our process. And it ties back actually to what we were discussing before about slowing down because you talk in the essay about, you say often the most important truths are not hidden because they're obscure, but because they're quiet, familiar and easy to pass by. So you talk about the work of, quote, seeing clearly what others overlooked, slowing down long enough to recognize what was already there.
Because that boat was there, that pirate ship I think had sunk in 1717. And so, you know, 250 or so years longer, it had sat there. So in terms of like what you saw of the process from watching someone like this treasure hunter, who was your dad's friend Barry, what did you learn about the process of finding stuff, finding buried treasure, which is really what you're doing in the stock market? Yeah.
Process gets back to what you had said earlier, which is that consecration of attention. We own less than 10 companies in our portfolio, so nine companies today. Each one of those is a found treasure. They're rare, right? To earn what we deem to be above, we're underwriting 15% or better IRRs over 10 years. And over our 16-year time,
period, we've been able to translate that objective into returns. Each one of those things has a lot that each one is a treasure that has to do a fair amount of heavy lifting over a long period of time. We treat it as such as you don't get, you have to focus that work so that when you have an opportunity that you can act with a sense of conviction and a sense of knowing that this is something that's actionable.
That's the process. And I saw that with Barry. I saw it with anyone that has done deep research, deep work, and then comes to the other side with a really high probability insight that's ideally probably non-consensus but right. That's really the work. Let's take a quick break and hear from today's sponsors. Curious about online trading, but haven't taken the first step yet?
You're not alone. And plus 500 futures is a great place to start. The futures markets are moving fast. And with plus 500, you can explore popular assets like oil, gold, S&P 500, Bitcoin and more. From crypto to commodities, there's always something happening. The platform is super easy to use so you can trade on the go right from your phone. You can get started with just $100 and jump into the action. See something interesting? Once your account is open, you can trade it in just a couple of clicks.
And if you're not quite ready yet, you can practice with a free demo account. No risk, no pressure. With 20 years of experience, PLUS500 makes trading more accessible than ever. Check it out at PLUS500.com. Trading and futures involves risks of loss and is not suitable for everyone. Not all applicants will qualify. PLUS500 is trading with a plus. They say every day your business is late to AI. You fall two days behind in the competition.
They're only moving faster. Fortunately, there's NetSuite Next. You probably already know NetSuite, the AI-powered business suite that securely connects all your data, financials, inventory, commerce, HR, and CRM all in one source of truth, trusted by over 43,000 customers. NetSuite Next is the next huge leap because now AI is built into everything you do. It surfaces custom insights throughout your day. AI agents work alongside you on the routine stuff.
And anytime you've got a question about anything, you just ask like you're talking to a colleague. And I use it and really I think you should too. For the first time ever, you can try NetSuite next for free. If your revenue is at least in the seven figures, go to net suite dot ai slash tip. Built for every industry ready for every boardroom net suite dot ai slash tip. As investors, we spend all day studying great businesses, but some of the best returns come from building one yourself.
If you've been sitting out a business idea, Shopify makes it easy to actually make it happen. Everything you need to start selling is included and ready from day one. Take the moment your first customer is ready to pay. Shopify checkout helps more of them finish the purchase. And when they come back, their details are already saved. One tap and they're done. And because Shopify handles the setup and the checkout, you get more time to focus on what actually grows the business plus the tools to do it.
If I were starting a business, I would absolutely use Shopify myself. It powers millions of businesses worldwide, from names like Mattel and Gymshark to founders just getting started at Shopify.com slash TIP. With Shopify, nothing stands between your idea and a real business. So go make it one. Start your free trial at Shopify.com slash TIP.
Start your free trial at Shopify.com slash TIP.
often looking at what's as you would put it hidden conspicuously not concealed but unrecognized and how these companies illustrate different principles. Of how you invest and so you know i think it's helpful to tether ourselves to the companies themselves because in some way otherwise the concepts can sound really theoretical and abstract but they're actually really important underlying laws and principles so i thought i would start by asking you about alphabet and.
you wrote at one point in your letter the end of the year letter alphabet remains one of the most extraordinary businesses ever built at its core it is a graph or as Americans would say it is a graph designed to organize the world's information and make it universally accessible and useful. And so this gets a really important theme for you which is this idea of of grass theory of graphs of edges and nodes and your folks on investing in graphs.
as they become stronger. Can you talk about that? Can you explain that way of looking at the world by telling us about alphabet? Because I actually, I think you've noticed something that's so fundamentally important and that as we go through this conversation, some of our listeners and viewers will start to realize, oh man, he's figured something out. Yeah, there's three pillars. You know, we look at the Grove of Titans, which is this universe of exceptional companies.
Each one of them we feel has three pillars and the three pillars is do they have a moat and is it widening? And we kind of deconstruct that. There's eight different layers of moat that we're looking for. And not that we want every company to have all eight, but we want layers of a competitive advantage that's identifiable and that we understand. And that as we're looking at that moat, we're like, is this something that's going to be still present 10 years from now in a different form?
So these things we want to have make sure they have a long shelf life. The second pillar is really secular tailwinds and secular meaning long term secular talents that's driving the top line growth of the business. We don't typically do a lot of things where they're facing secular headwinds that they're being disrupted by something. Even if we think that disruption may take some time, we usually avoid those things. So mode secular talents in the set in the last pieces.
is the human element. We want to partner with great operators that ideally have a history of pretty intelligent capital allocation. So, those three things give us a quality score on the business that we would put in that Grove of Titans basket that we're just spending our time really understanding. We're looking at 10-year valuations. We want to find something that's going to earn 15% rate of return from today's price over 10 years.
We measure that on free cash flow growth. And so when you get the quality at a reasonable price, there's usually clouds, right? There's clouds around the business that give you this opportunity to invest when perhaps there's some ambiguity in what the business is. So this is a little bit of a backdrop to understand Google because Google is probably one of the most extraordinary companies that's ever been built, as you noted that I said in the letter.
And the search business was designed and built around graph theory. And graph theory is something that, when you look at nodes and edges and how things scale, when nodes and edges are populating across a domain, we start to see increasing returns to scale. And I think that's one of the things that a lot of people have misunderstood about this period of technology is that
As these businesses have gotten bigger, they haven't run into this law of diminishing returns. Their growth has accelerated. Brian Arthur did this work at Santa Fe Institute, and we started to understand that what is present that is allowing for this increasing returns to scale? In our conclusion, there is a presence of a graph that's allowing for the information to grow and to grow exponentially.
through the nodes and edges that are available to it on the graph. And so when you look across and you start seeing things from a graph lens, you're like, oh, there's another graph. There's another graph. Amazon's a graph. Tesla, you know, we can talk about other things where graphs are present and that they're in the kind of the part of the S curve where that growth is now populating across the nodes and edges of what they've built. So yeah, Google search business is still a dominant
business for connecting ads to consumers. And it's allowed them to build a number of other businesses. Google Cloud now is an extraordinary business and going to be a bigger, bigger piece of the overall Google evaluation. We have YouTube, we have other businesses that have been built, right? We have Waymo. But at the core, when we got involved in Google, I think they were
I think their AI advantages was not as understood as it is now. And Demis Sassabis, in what he's built in DeepMind and in Google, is still in our perception as really leading an AI. Leading in not necessarily what we hear about Foundation Labs and building LLMs. Yes, we do that and we do that very well. But there's a large AI effort that Demis has led.
which is leading to all kinds of different applications we saw with Alpha Fold, healthcare breakthroughs, AGI, ASI. So we think there's a lot of things that are misunderstood about their AI advantages and how broad it is. Yes, I'll stop there if you want to add anything. Yeah. I mean, just to highlight a couple of points, there was a line you wrote, I think probably in your annual report where you said, much of our research effort is devoted to a simple question. Are the clouds temporary or permanent?
And so I think that gets at something really essential in your process that you're finding these businesses that have some underlying structure, as we'll discuss increasingly in this conversation, that's enormously powerful. But you're buying them at a moment where there's a kind of misperception that's leading the market to misprice them typically. Is that a fair summary? Yeah. The internal conversation that we have,
with any company that we own as we say, what are the clouds? How many clouds are there? What is our most important questions around those clouds? And then that's where a lot of our work lives. There's one thing to understand the competitive advantage and all of these things, but it's the clouds that really where we devote a lot of time and understanding, because that's where the misperception or the mispricing exists. So in the case of Google over the last couple of years, there was this
cloud around the blue links were going away all of our search eyeballs are gonna go to lm's and we're gonna move those eyeballs off the google platform onto open a i on enthropic and you had to understand that from first principles and and and to say is that is a true is that perception going to be a reality it's not yet. That's usually where we see this gap between perception in reality.
And that that's where the cloud lives. It's a perception that something might change versus evidence that it is. And so when we fast forward a year, what we realized is actually Google's their search volumes are going up with AI, not down. And that they were able through those eyeballs to bring more of their customers to look at AI tools, maybe the pioneers and look at LLMs.
We're downloading open AI and using chat GBT and so forth. But there's the whole middle of the bell curve that's experiencing AI for the first time through the Google search bar using different AI tools that are being shown to them and saying, oh, OK, this is interesting. We're going to download Gemini and others. So that cloud has dissipated. And last year, it translated into a lot of alpha generation for us.
The second cloud that was there was regulatory, was antitrust. FTC were going to break up Google in a way that would be disruptive to us in our long term, having this as one entity. So we had to look at that carefully and break down a probability array to understand that. We ended up getting an FTC ruling that was very much in our favor from the standpoint of taking that cloud away. It was almost like we woke up one day and the cloud was gone.
So again, that translated to a re-rating of the business. There was a point in time where we owned Google at 15 times earnings. And this thing is growing top line and all of these vectors of opportunity and asymmetry and what was possible and we're getting the best business in the world at this incredible price. So now we on Google store one of our largest holdings and it's a different array of clouds. It's a different array of understanding.
And every day we're just testing that hypothesis. Sometimes we think about our thesis. I think everything we own, we think about as a hypothesis. And how do we test that hypothesis to see if it's still true? And some days we wake up, say, you know, that hypothesis doesn't feel to be true. This other information comes in. And that might be a point where you'd want to exit an investment, even one that you've had for a very long time. There's a very timely
example of these clouds arising in the markets that you look at in the addendum which some published to your twenty twenty five year and later and you describe as the biggest cloud of twenty twenty six obviously is software and my sense is that in recent months you've been able to buy consolation software which is a stock that usually would be. Sort of unbiable for someone like you because of the price the valuation.
And in a way this gets at kind of the core of what it is that you do. Can you talk about the cloud there because it seems like an incredibly difficult cloud to analyze given the uncertainties about the future of AI and the impact that it's going to have on software. Tell us partly, you know, partly what you concluded about this stock in this sector, but also just how it illustrates your process of looking at clouds and trying to separate.
the perception from the reality. Yeah, and you can always feel into where the clouds are. Like we even have a title for this, right? William, it's the Software Apocalypse. I mean, how perfect? It is the biggest cloud of 2026. And it's scary. We have transformational technology in the form of AI coming to us every day there's a new model coming out. Every day there's the potential for an existing platform to be disrupted.
So what we try to do is we want to go where the clouds are thickest and understand there's something to do there that's intelligent. So constellation software, we've studied this business for over 10 years. I've known Mark Leonard, who's a legendary capital allocator, legendary operator. Had it in the classroom probably three times over our 15, over the last 10 years since I've known him.
When we went and looked at software, we didn't own a lot of software assets leading into this. Software is constellations trading off 50% off highs in the first quarter of this year. Rolled up our sleeves again, re-underwrote this business from first principles, but we have to still get to the heart of the disruption. We had to deconstruct what was a shallow mode in software and what was a deep mode.
It developed a framework which you read in that addendum. The purpose of writing that, as we talked about earlier, was to really understand this and to write it up so that we as a team could think about this as we looked across the software investments and where we wanted to do the what business we might want to own. We looked at that. There's eight different layers that we deconstructed that we thought
made something a shallow or deep mode. The first is your interface layer. That was the one that if you had a very shallow interface software company, AI could likely come in and be, you know, you could kind of vibe code something up and create a better interface. That made sense to us. That was a shallow mode. When we looked at horizontal software companies, we didn't want to own something that was horizontal and interface level. We wanted to own something that was vertical and deep. The second layer,
is the motion that software. So software as a service, how deeply is it embedded in the motion of the enterprise? The third was the memory, like how much institutional memory is involved in how the software is integrated into the business. The next one, next layer, again, we keep going deeper is the orchestration layer. How deeply is it orchestrated among different partners, different APIs that are connected? The next is resilience layer. So
security protocols all the different how deeply it's integrated into the data being safe and protected and stored. The trust layer who you have someone that's on the other side of the phone if something goes wrong with your software how capital is allocated across that software business how has it been what are they building what are they improving and then the learning layer just kind of integrated in the flywheel of learning and building software.
So that was our deconstructed vertical into understanding from software asset to software asset who had these attributes. And the people who are eagle-eyed or eagle-eared will note that those letters, it can all be summed up in this acronym, Immortal, which is very, very typical of you. Explain what you're doing there because you've done this before where you talk about things like the Piper mindset, which is
perpetual persistent incremental progress eternally repeated right it's like a way of remembering ordering information it's another distillation right a synthesis of very complex information a compression. I always like to think of a memory tool that is helpful in bringing to bear this framework repeatedly on something so like our our essence of mode.
is a seven layer framework that happens to spell essence. Or I've helped create words to express very important parts of those layers of mode. And the same with, you know, system of record vertical market software. As we deconstructed it, we're like, okay, this is a helpful way for us to kind of take this learning and apply it across the domain of software. I happened to just return from Egypt and
We were in the new museum in Cairo and the funeral apparatus of Barry and King Tut was fresh in my mind. And it was just, I was so shocked at how they thought about immortality. And immortality was something that they planned their entire life around. And King Tut not only was he in these different mummy forms, but the number of different caskets.
that were there to protect the body. It made me think of like, that's what we're looking at in software, really. We're looking at all of these different layers to allow for these businesses to be to endure. We talked about earlier, endure. And Mark Leonard built a system that really spoke to endurance, and that hadn't changed. The cloud that is still resident around software,
is a perception that these assets could be disrupted versus any evidence that they are. If we were to see churn numbers accelerate in the individual businesses that Constellation owns, we'd start being concerned. They had their first investor day in Toronto, which I took my whole team to. Got to know Mark Miller, who's now taking over the leadership role, met with a bunch of the different division heads. And so we've spent a lot of time over the last three and four months to
to deconstruct this and look for evidence where is this a perception of the cloud or is this a real cloud? And the hypothesis is holding. We've bought two software assets this year. And as you know, these in a nine company portfolio. And in the midst, William of cloud, it's always like in meta and 22 or perimeter, like whatever the cloud of the year is, it's always feels the same when you're in it.
like a year from now, two years from now, we'll have a conversation now. I can say, okay, we were right on this or that, or maybe we misunderstood something, but we're in it right now. And this feels the patterns and feeling feels like this is going to be a very productive investment for us. But we'll see. Well, last time we spoke on the podcast, which I would encourage people to go back and listen to.
i think it was literally on the day of the tariff tantrum announcements when the markets were melting down and you were i guess in the midst of buying tesla and amazon tesla much more detested than amazon which will will get to in in a few minutes but i think the point i wanted to pause on an emphasize with constellation software is something you wrote in this addendum where you said you need to slow down look again and recognize what has been built layer by layer over time.
And so what we're talking about here is that there was a kind of moat that as you explained in that, a dendym relies on dense interdependencies. It's really difficult to rewire the holes. So maybe there's like a little bit that is very vulnerable, but to rewire the whole thing is unbelievably difficult. And so again, it's something where as you put it in that piece of writing, perception outruns evidence. Does that raise any thoughts for you, any comments on that?
As we talk to some of these vertical market software business that are system of record assets that have this deep layer of interdependency, the other thing I'll add is that what we're finding is AI isn't necessarily the threat, but actually could be deployed on top of this in an ontological layer that improves their business proposition to their customers.
We're seeing more evidence of that as we're talking to, say, Jan Moore of Chakras Group or Mark Miller and his team, is that they're seeing more opportunities where AI can be deployed in a way to add more value. Maybe some of that value added could translate into additional revenue sources. We'll see. We see more evidence that AI is actually helping them and helping them at this point.
I think part of what's interesting also that's worth emphasizing is that you have this competitive advantage that comes from a network of people who become really valuable sources. Some of it through teaching for I guess the last 15 years now right at Columbia and so I remember when I sat in on your on a class yours a few months back I'm sure before the consolation software purchase on the day the next week came to speak.
Alexis Fortune also came to speak. I guess if I remember rightly, Dublin based investor who runs a firm called Blacksheep. And he had an enormous position in constellation software. And so I'm sort of thinking, you had Mark Leonard come through three times who's sort of almost impossible to get an interview with. How does that work where you have this kind of mastermind group around a business or a sector that you're investigating?
It's incredibly helpful and important. I've had a close, one of my best friends owns an extraordinary software business in Rufin. Helping and being part of his leadership around that business over the last 10 years is also another... It gives you a different layer of insight versus maybe what you can glean as a public equity investor.
But yeah, the network, the network's really, really, really valuable. What we tend to do on a weekly basis is we kind of have an understanding of what our questions are, what are our MIQs, what are our most important questions, and who can help us answer those. So we, every Monday, we kind of create a hierarchy of those questions that we're seeking answers to, and we go find those people. And oftentimes those contacts are in our network, and we can reach out
have a conversation. That leads to another conversation and you just keep doing it. And then you understand, okay, let's prioritize what are the MIQs now with this investment or this new thing we're looking at. And the network becomes invaluable. And 15 years of doing the class, as you noted, it's been transformational in having a deeper connection with a group of investors and operators that you've kind of done this thing together with the students.
you've built some trust and it allows for those conversations just to come naturally. I think that whole idea of trust is really, really interesting. And when you came to talk in Omaha, I was hosting a celebrating Charlie Munger event, I guess on May 1st, that probably I guess it was the night before the annual meeting, the Q&A. And you and I chatted at some length on stage about the seamless web of deserved trust, this idea of charlotte's. And I think it's worth pausing and
dwelling on it a bit because I reread a chunk of your essay on it. And it's such an important idea. And Charlie famously had said that the highest and best culture is a seamless web of deserved trust. And he talked about the Mayo Clinic as an example of this. And he just said, you know, there's not much procedure. It's just totally reliable people correctly trusting one another. Can you talk about this idea that you drew?
from Charlie I think that trust is a long duration asset and that it's full value appears only over time as you put it. Yeah, I think one of the most important insights from physics is understanding entropy or where friction lives and when you reduce friction or reduce entropy in any system. You allow more information to flow through that system and when more information is flowing values being created.
So a seamless web of deserved trust allows for more information to flow more easier, more fluid. And it was like this, you see it at Berkshire, you know, in 20 to 40,000 people show up and that collective feeling that they've created over 50 years is a feeling of trust. It's deserved trust. It's doing the right thing when no one else is looking. And that allows for other emergent
things to happen. I'll sell my company to Berkshire and not this other company because I trust them. I trust that they're going to honor this relationship I've built with my employees. They're going to honor or act honorably for a long period of time. And so I think it's the most important thing a young person can do is to operate with such a level of
you want to get to that point to be trustworthy, to deserve trust of your friends, your family, your whoever you're interacting with. And because you've shown up, you've done the right thing countless times, you've done it when no one else is looking. And then I think the emergent things that happen after you've lived a long time doing that is pretty remarkable. And it's hard to point to it like linearly, but you have this
exponential outcome that is, it's hard to point, oh yeah, this led to this led to this. And it creates these moments of just really amazing luck that follows you. Yeah, it's an overwhelming benefit. And I think I wrote about it in Richard Wisehap here is what I called the mench effect. Like if you're a mench, if you're just a kind decent person, it has this kind of compounding effect.
there was a paragraph from your essay on trust about the compounding of trust that I think is such a beautiful insight that I'm going to read it because I think if people really deeply internalize this idea, it's one of those things where, as Charlie said to Nick Sleep, I can only teach people what they already almost know. This is something we already almost know, but it's like, oh, it's a deep truth. So I'm going to read this paragraph that you wrote, which I really love, where you said,
The trustworthy person does not simply become more liked, they become more usable by the world. More people can rely on them, more responsibilities can flow through them, more opportunities gather around them. They become in effect a stronger node in the graph of human relation. Where deserved trust compounds long enough, something like a super node emerges, a person or institution through which extraordinary amounts of coordination, goodwill, capital,
truth and responsibility can move because the surrounding network has learned that the flow will not be casually corrupted. And then you said something really beautiful that I really love where you said the deepest question we can ask in any enduring bond is, quote, can I safely place part of my life in your hands? I think that's such a profound question to ask when you're investing with someone. You know, you, I mean, I place part of my retirement with you and
So, I mean, that's literally me looking at you and saying, can I safely place part of my life in your hands? And so, I think you're getting at something hugely important. And, you know, when I first read that essay after you sent it to me, I remember texting you back and saying that I think being trustworthy in some way is an expression of unconditional love because it's sort of dropping one's own agenda and caring for others and putting their interests first. And I think maybe it's so unusual in the business and investing world.
When you see it, you're like, oh man, that's powerful. And it's everything. And we certainly ask that question of every company that we're invested in. And when you own less than 10 companies, you can't make a mistake. Every investment has to be asymmetrical. And you're ultimately making a decision. You're making a discernment of the operator to act in a trustworthy way that you can
that you respect their judgment. The last essay that I've written is called Keystone. And Keystone, just thinking about an arch, right? If you look at an arch, there's something in the arch that's doing a lot of... It's the Keystone in it. And the Keystone for me is judgment. And as we have some of these tools available to us where we're allowing AI, maybe an LLM to contextualize something,
there's a chance to lose the connection with the source material. And when you're removed from the source material, it's very hard to discern judgment. And it was something that we've purposely built a small team, a three member investment team. And the design of the architecture of that is so that we can share in the learning together of the source material. I'm not outsourcing a reading to a sector analyst.
I want to be part of the reading so that we can all come to conclusions about quality, about valuation by touching source material. The minute you give an LLM or an agent or some analyst sectorist over here to read that source material and interpret it, I think you lose that connection with something that's really valuable. And so, judgment and trust come together. Ultimately,
I think if you're allocating capital to someone, you're trusting that that judgment is going to continue to be well founded. You mentioned the word source and you talk about architecture a lot. You often talk about this word that you've coined, source built. You wrote in one of your essays about the Sagrada Familia Cathedral in Barcelona and also about St Paul's Cathedral in London.
about how there are these timeless buildings that sort of survive because in some sense that sauce built and that there are rare businesses that are also source built and you said one question that's been central to you. Is quote why do some things keep gathering forces time passes through them while others begin to die almost as soon as the novelty wears off. Can you talk about this concept of things being so because it's usually important and it's not in a sense it's.
It's not self-evident. It requires some unpacking. But I think it runs through all of these things you're discussing. Yeah. And I think for a long time, the working title of some of the essays was called Edge Node, where I was applying graph theory to the understanding of different laws and observations. It's morphed to the working title is called Source Built. When I think about that,
which is built from first principles or aligned with nature, aligned with how the world works. It's aligned with source. It's aligned with that foundational structure, that architecture. I had known that there was purpose built. We talked about things that are purpose built. Source built felt something that was much more foundational. It came from a different grounding. It was aligned with very, very long
a long thread that went through human history and biology and chemistry and physics. And you could trace that thread all the way back to the beginning, 13.7 billion years of data, right? And that's what I'm referring to as source belt. And I think if you're following that source belt thread, yes, you can follow it into investing. You can follow it into your relationships. You can follow it into teaching. So the word though,
William, which I may have shared this with you. I discovered it when I was working with my favorite philosopher named Heraclitus. And so I was reading a lot of Heraclitus's fragments at the time. It was one of my quarterly deep dives. I had a couple deep dives going at the time. I was thinking about arches and I was thinking about Heraclitus. And I was reading these fragments, different sources, different translations. And Heraclitus was known as Heraclitus the Obscure.
And he was known as the obscure because he would often work with paradoxes where there'd be multiple truths that you were holding at the same time. And he understood this as being really important philosophical underpinning of the world. And as I'm looking at Heraclitus the Obscure, literally the letters, I'm like, am I seeing something? I see arches. I was like, that's interesting. Arches is in Heraclitus the Obscure. I'm like, what else is in there? I'm like, the arches. Well, that's cool.
And then all of a sudden I see the word built. I'm like, oh, this is starting to get a little weird. And then I am like, oh, what's left? I rearrange the letters and it's source. The source built arches is an anagram of Heraclitus the obscure. I literally fell off my seat. And I was like, I'm like, oh, is source building a word? It's kind of like purpose built. And so that was my first relationship with the word source built. And
It was such a beautiful discovery and it stayed with me. So it gets a sense of an underlying structure. I mean, I was trying to put this together from your various essays and there's a line where you're describing Source Built and you say it's aligned with a prior order with the way reality bears weight, carries life, transmits force, joins weakness into strength and allows more to pass through than the builder alone could have planned.
I mean it's interesting it reminds me in some ways of Nick sleep would often say you know who's a beautiful friend of ours would often talk about. When the world is working the way it should you know i'm slightly. Miss quoting him the world working right there's a sense of a sort of underlying structure of things it's like it's like you know charlie always talking about win-win. Relationships which you talk about as well as like all companies like cost goes to making enormous amounts of money and then sharing.
those benefits with their customers and creating a flywheel by having this pattern of scale, economy, shared as Nick and Zach figured out. You feel as if you've kind of connected with some underlying principle of life. Yeah, that's it. That idea of the general law. So if you think of an arch, right? An arch is, this is Da Vinci's definition of an arch is, two weaknesses brought together to create a strength.
And so if you think of an arch, well, what's the utility of an arch? Well, a lot of things can move through an arch. It could be a portal. You could create a door, a portal. You could build a bridge. You could build a dome. And so you mentioned Segrada Familia and Gaudi and Christopher Ran of St. Paul's Cathedral. At the highest application of an arch, this dome-like quality can be built. And that to me is source-built.
It's what can we do when these wind wind structures come together and align with these principles of how things grow and grow better. And so it's been kind of a guiding principle to kind of find these dome-like qualities in business and in systems. And then when I find them, they're source built by nature. Let's take a quick break and hear from today's sponsors.
One part of being an investor that I don't think gets enough attention is how hard it can be to continue to improve as an investment researcher. And for myself, I often find that when I finish a great conversation with some industry expert or fund manager, my head is full of ideas. But by the time I sit down to write it all up, half of them are already gone. That's why I've been using Plod Note Pro.
It's a small device that sticks to the back of my phone and captures the conversation and hands me back a clean, searchable recap. And so the key points, the follow-ups, the things I usually want to act on, it has all of that. And that allows me to stay present in the room and set a scribbling notes that I won't be able to read back later. And I notoriously have very bad handwriting. And so it's changed how I prep and how I follow up with investors. It's also built for people who take conversation seriously. Enterprise grade security.
So if you're recording calls with clients or industry contacts, that's covered too. So if you live in meetings, calls and interviews, we'll give it a look. Go to plod.ai slash WSB and use code WSB for 10% off. That's plod.ai slash WSB code WSB and always get consent before you record a conversation. They say every day your business is late to AI, you fall two days behind and the competition
They're only moving faster. Fortunately, there's NetSuite Next. You probably already know NetSuite, the AI-powered business suite that securely connects all your data, financials, inventory, commerce, HR, and CRM all in one source of truth. Trusted by over 43,000 customers. NetSuite Next is the next huge leap because now AI is built into everything you do. It surfaces custom insights throughout your day. AI agents work alongside you on the routine stuff.
And anytime you've got a question about anything, you just ask like you're talking to a colleague. And I use it and really I think you should too. For the first time ever, you can try NetSuite next for free. If your revenue is at least in the seven figures, go to netsuite.ai slash tip. Built for every industry, ready for every boardroom, netsuite.ai slash tip.
Curious about online trading but haven't taken the first step yet? You're not alone. And Plus 500 futures is a great place to start. The futures markets are moving fast and with Plus 500 you can explore popular assets like oil, gold, S&P 500, Bitcoin and more. From crypto to commodities, there's always something happening. The platform is super easy to use so you can trade on the go right from your phone. You can get started with just $100 and jump into the action.
See something interesting? Once your account is open, you can trade it in just a couple of clicks. And if you're not quite ready yet, you can practice with a free demo account. No risk, no pressure. With 20 years of experience, plus 500 makes trading more accessible than ever. Check it out at plus500.com. Trading and futures involves risks of loss and is not suitable for everyone. Not all applicants will qualify. Plus 500. It's trading with a plus.
So I think as people are starting to sense part of what you're up to is you're looking for these underlying structures that are emerging that are sort of the world working as it should. And one of the most controversial investments, possibly the most controversial investment you've made was a new investment you made in 2025 that you've been researching since the fall of 2023, which was Tesla. And when we spoke, I think our last interview was on April 2nd, 2025, I lost into you on the podcast at least.
it was at the absolute height of the controversy and people should go back and listen to that because I you know we talked about it in some depth but can you talk about how tesla. Is kind of this perfect example of something emerging some structure emerging or a series of structures. You know merchant graphs or graphs as you would say or as I would say these these emerging graphs that others aren't necessarily.
recognizing in all of these different businesses because I think this is such a beautiful example of separating the signal from the noise and kind of looking to see beyond all the controversy about Elon and all of the controversy about the valuation that there's some structure emerging that we would do well to recognize and linger on. Yeah, when you had, I remember getting ready for the interview in April 25 and you're like, I'm going to ask you about Tesla and I was like,
Oh, William, please don't ask me about Tesla. And then I think just before we went on, I'm like, ask me about that. That'll be fine. And we were able to unpack it in a way, I think, that was also, it was at a time where I think a lot of people were feeling the tension that was what was happening politically in the country and more broadly. And it was hard. And I had put a circle around Tesla. I had put a circle around Elon and found
that he was uninvestable. I had an opinion about that for a long time and I think I shared in the podcast that I had gone on a retreat with a group of investors turns their mountain. We go every year and to long walk retreat and we spend time just talking through things and I was asked to moderate a panel and I left that experience saying, you know, I had to go back and do my own work to understand this because a couple of people I respect a lot had come to a very different conclusion.
And if they were right, this would be very, very important. And it actually would click a lot of the things that we look for in our growth of titans type business, and it was misunderstood. So I left that experience, spent a couple of years, took me a lot of unpacking to get to a place where I thought it became investable, or at least my understanding of it did. And certainly the sell-off in that April 25 period gave us a window.
And it continues to this day. It's a very important material position in the portfolio. I think about it in terms of five, there's really five businesses that are a really important order to Sanford, Tesla alone. And that's their, you know, their core EV business, which is a means to an end. And that's been something that's building for, you know, well over a decade that is an enabling technology to do
something else. And that something else is full self drive. Basically, they've created a platform and built software that will allow for autonomy to scale globally. And whether through personal transportation, you could own a Tesla and full self drive as software as a service can drive you around. That's available today. The next extension of this is going to be RoboTaxi.
And Robotaxi today is rolling out in cities across the country, eventually across the world, Austin, first, San Francisco, Miami recently announced the last couple of weeks. We're at a point where the software has solved autonomy. I think 1% of the world actually understands this exists. It's solving autonomy translates into, if you look at the data, I think it's going to be about 10 times safer than a human driver.
So there's a safety backed by data incentive to have this technology regulatory wise, maybe even as a personal car driver, you may choose safety. I was thinking about this today about at what point did we start wearing helmets when biking? And if this is a 10x safer technology than a human driver, perhaps there's even a greater incentive to
to have a larger amount of driving that's done autonomously. One of the questions that we had asked in class last year, and I asked every guest because it was interesting how the answers changed over the course of the semester, I said, what percent of total miles driven globally will be autonomous in 10 years? I think the student group answered that about five or 10%. A lot of our guests, including James Anderson said,
formerly with the LA Gifford and Deval Shroff at Tesla's autonomy division, their answers were over 80%. If you think of that end-state question and you work backwards, technology tends to be where you take most. If Tesla is the only general solution for autonomy versus, say, Waymo, which is a different set of how they've solved it, this is a general intelligence. What does that mean for cheaper, better, faster, safer, robotaxi?
That's one component of the hypothesis that as that rolls out will be much clearer to investors and to the profitability of the business. The last piece, we won't have to talk about Tesla Energy, but that's another... No, we should talk about that too because it's another beautiful example of an emergent graph, right? Yeah. Yeah, the Tesla Energy is basically a grid 2.0, emergent, and that's thinking about how do we store and smooth out our energy usage.
more and more of our energy will be generated through solar and we need batteries. We need large-scale batteries and Tesla is purpose-built to deliver large-scale battery storage and they've been very, very successful at building capacity and rolling this out globally. That will continue to be a very important piece of Tesla. This is actually built by JB Straubel as a kind of a Skunkworks project.
And we got to meet JB together and Elon's like, JB, what are you doing? You got to shut that down. Let's focus. We got a lot of things we got to work on. And JB kept building that business. And now it's going to be a very important, not just important business for Tesla, but it's important business for the world to have that kind of storage capability. And Tesla can do it at scale better than anyone. The fifth business, which is the humanoid robot, is going into production this year and
we have a V production level product ready to come out. So you have two legs of the stool of the five that are probably going to drive 80% of the value creation just kind of moving into the sweet spot of the beginning of their S curves. And that's kind of happening this year into next year. So Tesla's a very exciting business.
I look at these technologies as inevitable, not VC. Like I wonder if they can build this. No, they've done it. I wonder if they could build Optimus. They've done it. We have a V production ready. With Optimus, there's three things you have to get right. You have to build a dexterous hand that has 22 or more degrees of freedom. They've done that. You need to have the capability to produce at scale. Tests has proven they can build factories better than anyone. And then the third piece is the intelligence.
And they had the intelligence capability built from their autonomy, AI, that they can deploy into Optimus. So we think they're very well positioned for this next move into robotics, which will be very important for them. You and I had a conversation in Goodwood a couple of years ago with our mutual friend, Frederick Blackford, who I'm grateful to you for introducing me to a really lovely, lovely human being. And the wonderful James Anderson, who's this great...
investor from Bailey Gifford originally, although now Lingotto is it? And we talked about Tesla among other things as an example of what you and they have started to call value 3.0, this sort of shift, this great leap from Ben Graham who was value 1.0 to Warren and Charlie value 2.0 and now value 3.0. Can you talk about Tesla as kind of an example of this? Because
old-fashioned people like me that sort of pure sort of always asking you also where's the margin of safety where's the margin of safety. And in some ways, you know, you're the torch bearer for Ben Graham as the person running his class. And yet you're sort of you're looking at Tesla in a way that's very it requires a different set of skills, I think to look at it this way. Tell us how it embodies value 3.0. Everything that a value investor does
and thinks about has to be asymmetric. And so asymmetry is at the heart of value one, two and three. What is my margin of safety? What is the floor? How do I lose? How can I have permanent loss of capital? You buy something that's too expensive, you can result in a permanent loss of capital. You know, value one, you know, Ben was just saying, okay, I have a collection of assets, they're worth a
a dollar and I can buy him a 50 cents on the dollar, maybe less. Buffet, monger, let's buy a great business at a reasonable price. But that reasonable price might be, I can buy it at 10 times earnings or 12 times earnings for Apple. And I can own that for a long period of time. I don't have to buy, sell and reinvest. That's smarter than one. It's an extension of value investing. We can look to these levels of value eight and they're optically there. Value three,
And I think Nick was one of the torchbearers here, Nick Sleeves, when he was looking at Amazon real time in his Nomad letters was, okay, optically, Amazon didn't look cheap. You had to do some things, you had to add back some of the investments that they were making and understand what the margin potential of the business is to understand the true nature of the valuation. In hindsight, Amazon was one of the cheapest companies in the world.
It was compounding at 47% from that point. So we know that the toolkit that we had available, value two and value one, wasn't the full toolkit we needed to do this other type of investing that value three became. And then when we look at Google and we look at Meta and we looked at all these technology companies that just required a different lens of analysis, Tesla meets that. Right? I think when you
you have to understand at the inevitability of the core technologies with which that they are, that they're building. And this isn't a coin flip. If this works, then what? That's not what we do. That's why Tesla in its early days, I don't regret not investing at a time where James Anderson did, because that doesn't meet our criteria of inevitability. He may have seen it. We wouldn't have.
But there was a point where escape velocity was met in a business like Tesla where the technology, the platform, the foundation was built, and then there were vectors of asymmetry that emerged from that point. I don't like vectors of symmetry. I want vectors of asymmetry. In that past, in 25, probably into 24, those asymmetries became very clear. And I think we're in the early stages of those asymmetries playing out.
and the future is pretty exciting. I would say to underwrite Tesla today, you have to underwrite SpaceX as well. I think we have a likely, there's likely a merger within the next 12 months between Tesla and SpaceX. So we've spent a fair amount of our resources over the last year and understanding SpaceX and first principles, underwriting it and thinking about what does this look like as one entity.
And you had a back door investment in SpaceX through Echo Start, which I think had sold it's something like $11 billion worth of Spectrum assets to SpaceX. So you sort of had figured out there was a way to get access to SpaceX privately. In one of your pieces of writing, you said, SpaceX is one of the most extraordinary businesses we have ever examined. You said Starlink in particular represents one of the most powerful emergent graphs.
built in the past two decades. Can you talk about that again? Because again, it's like a beautiful example, I think, of once you start to see the world in terms of these underlying structures, these graphs and nodes, you kind of can't unsee it. So talk to us about SpaceX also as kind of an example of an emergent structure, an emergent system. And also maybe you could talk a little bit more about this idea of edge nodes, which I think are very relevant both to SpaceX.
and to Tesla right and explain to us what the concept is because again you need to repeat it a few times to me before I start to understand it it's a complicated idea. Yeah, yes, SpaceX is very special business and it's becoming more well known now that it's in the public markets now and being covered by lots of sell side firms and so forth. But there's still a lot of misinformation I think out there. But
At its core, you have a business that has built a launch capability in the form of a reusable rocket. That was a novel idea when they started that process, and it's revolutionized the ability to put payload to space. Prior to SpaceX, it would cost around $50,000 plus to put a kilogram to low earth orbit. What Falcon 9 allowed for was
you know, a kilogram to go into Leo for about $2,400. And what did that do? It allowed for them over the last six years to build Starlink. Starlink is a constellation now of 10,000 plus satellites producing really high bandwidth connectivity to the world. You could argue that this is kind of internet 2.0, nodes and edges, but now built
in a mesh around Earth that's cheaper, better, faster, safer is when you think of the, if we were to rebuild the internet 1.0 and you had the opportunity to do 2.0, would you dig up all the roads and put all the fiber optics? As you continue to densify the network of a constellation with laser link connectivity between it, what we're seeing is speeds are getting faster and faster and faster. And so more customers
that may have been fringe customers or maybe saying, yes, I'm going to opt for Starlink versus some other service that is available terrestrial to me. And so Starlink has been this really fabulous graph that's emerged from this launch capability. And what we have now is you have the next iteration of launch, which is Starship. Starship has the capability given size in both stages of reusability, first and second, to reach
I'll go from $2,400 a kilogram to Leo to $100 and potentially as low as $10. This cost curve, we study cost curves very carefully. When you look at this kind of cost curve, what happens when you see big changes in cost curves is you have a phase transition. And we're in the midst of a phase transition where things that were possible in space are now possible with Starship.
And so you have to have a view on, is Starship solved? Is V3 Raptor engines, V3 Starship, the unlock capability to get to this $100 a kilogram to lower the orbit? We believe it is. We believe the heat shield and other things are solved. And now we have an exclusive launch vehicle for an emergent space, which is everything off Earth, which allows for the next iteration of Starlink, which is going to include
direct to sell communications, maybe our phones. So all these nodes are now emergent for Starlink to form customers. We also have RoboTaxies coming online, Internet of Things. And so the more and more nodes that need to connect seamlessly to this graph will be business for SpaceX as we move forward. The other business that is being talked about now with SpaceX is it's in the business of compute.
So they have a real capability to build terrestrial compute faster than anyone else. And we saw this leading up to the IPO. They were able to sell some of their terrestrial compute to Anthropic and Google, big headline contracts. But the big win for them is going to be to move some of that compute from Earth to low Earth orbit. And in the form of their AI-1 satellite, which will be an orbital data center. And so the same graph
Remember, William, I always say, when there's an emergent graph, I pause and reflect. This is going to be one of the most important emergent graphs over the next five years is orbital data centers. And this isn't necessarily a hard problem. I'd say the satellite constellation is a harder problem than I think orbital data centers is, even though it sounds crazy that, wait, we can put data centers in space? So the path to that we think is a highly probable path.
and it could be transformational to the point where I think it'll be 75% cheaper to do an orbital data center than it would be a terrestrial data center. Again, a cost curve driving down, you're going to be the low cost producer of intelligence to the planet and that will be very valuable for SpaceX. When you encounter skeptics who just sort of look at you like you've drunk the Kool-Aid and you're buying into
Elon's capacity for hype and the capacity of Wall Street to hype IPOs and all of that stuff. You must have a lot of cognitive disnance that you have to deal with with this stuff. How do you respond to that stuff? Because there's something really complex here going on, which is important in the trajectory of value investing, which is that you're shifting from identifying mispriced assets to really focusing on value creation.
but you're doing it in quite an uncomfortably idiosyncratic way where people, you know, venture capitalists could understand what you're doing, but the sort of people who you and I traditionally have hung out with would look at you and be like, what the hell is he drinking? Yeah, if you look at the combined entity of Tesla and SpaceX, you're paying $3.2 trillion for a collection of 10 businesses. Five we mentioned for Tesla, five for SpaceX. And you have to
Think about all of those 10 vectors and say, in 10 years, what's the inevitability for that profitability? What's the range of that? And we've spent a lot of time in understanding that. What's the low end? What's the vector on the high end? And where does that range look like? We could literally fly a starship through that range right now. Like our internal models are almost comical because you're like, what?
I've never seen a range this wide. The midpoint of that range is very satisfactory. I think penciling out a 26 IRR in this investment is not hard to do. A 10X over 10 years, based on what we think the inevitability of those 10 business units are, we think it's a very highly probable outcome because we've done the work. It's not something that if someone told me that, I'd be like, that sounds crazy. But if you actually step back, you actually did the work and understand it, you might arrive at a similar
That's a reasonable reasonable assumption, but it took a while to get there. Yeah. I think there's something really profound going on here. And I remember having a conversation I've interviewed Bill Miller as you know, like many, many times over many years, starting with a profile that I wrote of him for Fortune when he had bought 15% of Amazon and the stock was at $6 a share. So we've been discussing these issues for a long time. And a few years ago, there was an event
for patient capital, I guess it was. Maybe it was the company before that that he was running for. It became Samantha Macklemore's company, Patient Capital. And I was interviewing him there. And I was trying to understand sort of the evolution of value investing sort of through his career. And I said to him, so you know, you had all these friends of yours like Chris Davis and the like, buying stuff at a huge discount to what it was worth. And is that sort of what you were doing? Is that the essence of what you were doing?
And this is his exact answer. He said to me, no, no, he said, for me, it's about buying them at a huge discount to what you believe they will be worth. And that seemed to me like a huge breakthrough in a way and kind of a controversial one. But that's what enabled him to buy 15% of Amazon, I think, among other things. Bill is an investor that I think has the best balance of right brain creativity and understanding where we're going seeing holes.
with connecting it to left-brain analytical. One of such a brilliant investor and I've learned so much from him just over the years and what he's shared. So, I love that answer because it's so true. It is so true. And it's how we think. Every single investment that we make, I think about what's the 10-year value on this? If I'm buying something in a billion, in 10 years, is this a $10 billion company?
One to 10, a 10x over 10 years is 26. Not everything we own is a 26 IR. A 4x is 15. So 15s are a threshold. We want to own things that are going to have between 4 and 10x. But that's the, I'm thinking about that end state inevitability is that what does it look like? Can this business look like a 10x over 10 years?
and then working backwards and connecting and looking at probabilities. So yeah, that's how we think about it. I think you get it something really interesting also when you talk about right brain thinking and Bill Miller and Teser is such a beautiful example in a way of right brain thinking because you can't just model it. And I was sort of curious how in some ways it grows out of having had the great, yeah, McGillchrist come into your class, you know, who's obviously an expert on
on the brain and how to think and the idea that the left brain has kind of come to dominate society and that we're paying a price for it. Can you unpack that a little bit? Because I think it gets us something really important about investing where there is the very rigorous sort of model building left brain kind of logical stuff and then there's this sort of slightly wilder, more creative side. Yeah. So, Ian McGillchrist in his work with the Matter with Things and the Mastering in his emissary,
has really unpacked an understanding of the brain and how the brain works. And our brain isn't symmetrical where the left is doing the same work as the right. The left has actually a languaging brain. It's our analytical brain. It's the thing that can focus on something and look at it. We know this through stroke victims, right? They've studied stroke victims and a left brain stroke leaves the patient unable to talk. A right brain is creativity. It's context.
a right brain stroke, you have inability to actually interact with the world. You become disoriented. You really have no context and understanding, and it's a much more severe stroke. Civilization has become much more left brain. We think that's the... has happened because of our language. As we've developed more human language and interacting with language, is that our left brain muscle gets activated more than our right brain. And so,
we see this in handedness, right? Right handedness is more left brain and more people are right hand and left hand, left handed. And so I always say like to try to balance your weak spot. If you happen to be more left brain, how do you to nurture your more creative side, your ability to to think more broadly and more context to see the whole? But sometimes you can't. And I think as an industry, analytical people are drawn to investing.
And I'd say over 70% of the students that come through the security analysis class that I'm stewarding are left brain. And that's normal, right? We can build spreadsheets, we can model the best investors, William, as you know, are the Bill Miller for the world, the Nick Sleeps of the world. They're the ones that are thinking very creatively about the whole. And that, I think, is a real superpower in
you know, building a long-term track record that's going to outperform and add alpha. And I think, you know, I've observed that Charlie was a right-brain thinker. And so even though Warren was more left-brain oriented, he partnered with the most incredible right-brain person I've ever encountered. And the combination was a lala-pallusa. And so it's pretty brilliant. Sometimes you get your complimentary person
It can be sometimes hard because you have these frictions of not being able to disagree and commit. But Warren and Charlie kind of developed a great partnership where they could disagree and commit and Charlie just like, okay, you do what you want Warren. But he would have his input. I don't know if I can articulate this question properly, but in some ways I keep thinking of you.
as a connoisseur of these underlying structures these systems these graphs that you've identified not just in the companies we've discussed so far but also in all of the other companies that we could have discussed whether it's perimeter solutions or trans dime or amazon there's always some underlying structure that you're identifying you know maybe it might be a company that's just unbelievable delivering stuff incredibly effectively or.
incredible persistent incremental improvement over time. So you're always looking for these systems. And I'm kind of wondering when you look at your own life, your life as an investor, but your life beyond investing, if you think about how to structure it as a sort of system that creates long-term value. Because I'm sure in some way, even though you don't talk about it publicly,
You're applying the same way of thinking, the same perspective, the same ability to look at systems and structures that create value. I'm sure you're thinking of your life in that way. Yeah. Everything should be a fractal of the optimal system. Yeah, you had asked earlier about edge nodes as well. And Persig's work on thinking about dynamic quality is about that leading edge of the train, right? That leading edge is the leading edge of
of quality that's emergent in front of you. That's why I think about the edge node, right? The edge node is also this emergent intelligence that is increasingly becoming robotaxy, optimist. These aren't just passive nodes, they're edge nodes. They have intelligence, they're working on the edge, and they're giving that learning back to the swarm the way like you might see in a beehive. So systems, edge node systems, dynamic quality on the edge,
or definitely like we're trying to find them everywhere. And we're trying to design a life that also has these qualities, right? That you're constantly learning, you're sharing the learning, you're applying these in different domains, whether it be a hobby or whether it be the classroom or whether it be in the craft of studying companies. And that word dynamic is the moving one, right? It's the
every day, you have to assume that everything's changing. And that's the thing that Persig tried to point out is if you think you know the answer, that answer is going to be stale, like tomorrow. It's the testing, it's the moving it forward, it's that scientific inquiry to continue to get more data, more information. And that's that persistent incremental progress, eternally repeated, is the edge node in practice. It's the practice
that you're bringing to your life and to your partnerships, to your friends. And that's fun. I think that's what all of your listeners are trying to do the same thing. They're listening to these conversations to try to pick up little things that they can do to improve and to add value to their lives and to their life design. I think in some way, the paradox is something shifts when you switch from just focusing on yourself and getting ahead yourself and you start to be like,
how do i bring back this good knowledge and understanding to the system to help the network improve and in a way like this i'm not articulating it properly and you can help me explain properly but there's something in the way that you think about. A tesla car with its eight cameras or whatever it is reporting back to the system to the network to improve the network individual is also in some way subservient.
to this larger network, this larger system. And when the world works properly, you're not just thinking of yourself, you're coming back and you're kind of using it to help the swarm. Yeah. And the strangest thing my wife or someone might observe our industry and while you're in the real time is like, wait, those are your competitors and you're sharing all your information with your competitors. I'm like, yeah, that's what we do. It's such a fun expression.
to share and to be part of the journey together with others. And there's a beautiful tradition. And I think Warren was one that was always sharing almost all of his insights. And you could take them, you can copy, you could build on the Berkshire if you wanted. But... And Ben Graham was unbelievably generous. Warren always talks about Ben Graham's generosity and sharing his insight. So the tradition is long. And it
It's a beautiful craft. Some of your listeners are some of the best at this craft. And to know you can do this for a very long time and to give back. And what it's always driven me is the puzzles, right? Like solving the puzzles is really enjoyable. It's not necessarily for some financial reward or even some mark of, but just going about this and trying to solve it is more than what's intellectually stimulating.
things I've encountered in my life. One of the things I've really been enjoying over the last few days is listening more concertedly to your music. I don't really understand how it comes about like what role AI plays and what, you know, like I'm sort of assuming that you're writing all the lyrics and you've written like over 150 songs I think and probably way more now. And I don't know what's happening. But some of it is really, really good. And in many ways, you would contribute to me not being able to sleep one night because I had one of your songs.
going through my head a lot which is probably my favorite of your songs which is called the great work. And it gets a lot of these issues of a sort of greater purpose of a, you know, and it's important in a number of ways. And you wrote about it in the addendum, this sense of the great work. And you said the great work is not scale for its own sake. It's not speed. It's not optimization. It is purpose carried patiently across time. Is the act of building something meant to last longer than the builder.
something that survives not because it is protected, but because it is true. Can you talk a little bit about that song? And also your experience of playing it in Egypt on your trip, because I think it gets at something essential about how you view your career, how you view your work, what it is you're trying to do, the type of companies that you're investing in, trying to identify things that are true and durable.
The songwriting has come over the last couple of years. And as we talked about earlier, writing is a compression of ideas and experiences that you can put and learn from as you're writing. And poetry was an extension of this. And I've always played with poetry and not something I published, but just something I enjoy doing and just playing with the words and how they make you feel. And I love music. I've always loved music.
but I've never considered myself a musician. Someone introduced me to the idea that one of the AI platforms, you can actually put lyrics in and you get this output of hearing a song. And the minute I did that, I was like, oh my goodness, this is this is wild. And because the songwriting was just an extension of poetry. It was an extension of kind of compressions of of words and feelings and experiences that then you could take with you. You can listen to them.
So it's been one of the most creative parts of my life because of playing with making these songs. And, you know, the great work was a song that came in my preparations for going to Egypt. And I was thinking about these places that we were going to visit. And the first place we were going to visit was the Great Pyramid of Giza. And we were having an opportunity to walk into the King's Chamber. And I was thinking about the Great Pyramids.
What ended up happening is I wrote an album that became called The Great Work, but it was a song for every place that we were going to visit. So every temple in tomb, I was trying to get to the underlying essence of what that, why was that place built? What did it mean? What was the essence of it? And these songs emerged and it was such a fun project because it became part of my pre-travel. And I didn't even publish the album until I got back.
And I'm listening to these songs and I was the first place we visited, we went to the Great Pyramid and I'm in the King's Chamber and I'm like, it kind of came to me. I'm like, I think I'm supposed to listen to the song in the Great Pyramid and quietly kind of in the corner of the King's Chamber, which is a pretty difficult, if anyone, any listeners have been in there, very claustrophobic experience, kind of getting into the center of the pyramid. And I'm listening to this in the corner and I just started to like
tears start crying down my eyes. It was such a moment. Then I realized, oh, I'm supposed to listen to all these songs in situ in the place I wrote them for. And it was such a cool experience. But the great work is, I was thinking about what, why were these pyramids built? Like what was being said there? What was the enduring objective of it? And it kind of
kind of maybe realize like everything that we're doing here you the writing of your books in the podcast and investing in teaching is just all part of like our expressions of doing this kind of this great work. Yeah, I found myself kind of because I'm obsessed with and fall down rabbit holes when I'm preparing for this interviews I found myself using author to transcribe your lyrics and. You know so I was struggling you saying we're here for the great work not the small self and put your heart in the flame and.
you said we were never meant to stand alone. And so there's this sense that I think of, you know, in some ways you can take the investing process and make it a very solitary kind of rapacious business where it's all just sitting and trying to maximize your returns at everyone else's expense. And I think what's kind of interesting is you found this way to make it sort of more of a team sport where there's less of it's not really a zero sum game. And what's also curious, you know, when I was reading the addendum of your
year-end letter and you're writing about the great work is a lovely line related to this way said we are students of endurance. Amateur archaeologists in a way studying what is survived and asking why searching for patterns of permanence trying to recognize the structure systems and builders are oriented towards something beyond immediacy that searches our research the internal discipline it requires is our own great work. I saw those really interesting there's a sort of.
there's a thread that runs through so much of what you do that you're really interested in buildings that have endured. You're interested in boats that have endured. You're interested in pyramids where people have been buried properly so there were layers of defences so that they wouldn't just get robbed. Do you have thoughts about that? Just comments on my
my observation of this thread that runs through everything, the type of companies that you're investing in. No, I think that duration has just been this thread that has run through everything. And it doesn't feel like it's... I want to leave a legacy for some egoic reason, but what is the extension of... I think it's such a deeply embedded trait of ours when you look at
DNA or any other method with which we encapsulate something and then hand it on to the next generation. It feels like, I don't know, there's a certain sense of joy in it, isn't there? It's like you're part of what you're supposed to do here. You're supposed to make the world a little better and then to hand on what you've learned to others and allow that thread to continue. And that feels good. Every person I've ever invited into the classroom, and these are
Fortune 100 CEOs or doesn't matter how they look like a kid to me when we're sitting before our conversation on a fireside chat. They want to have a great experience. They want the students have a great experience. And there's no ego in that moment. It's just it kind of feels very like a free verse principle. So yeah, I think it's I think it all connects to this idea of longevity and duration. Yeah. And David Hawkins terminology, it kind of makes you go strong.
You know, exactly. Exactly. And I think one of my favorite essays of yours that I read this week is one on scarcity, which sort of starts with you talking about the oddity of being in Essex, Massachusetts and seeing these two amazing Ferrari 250 GTOs, which I think are now worth about $60 million each and only like 36 of them exist. And so this led you to sort of think about the rarity of things and what makes something sort of precious. And there's a
There's a line I wanted to read because I think it gets at something very different that you're up to here where you talked about how scarcity in its instinctive forms sees every interaction as zero sum. Someone wins, someone loses. And then you said, but the game I want to play in markets and in life is different. I want to play with people and businesses capable of durable mutual benefit of operating on a horizon long enough for trust, curiosity, generosity and real alignment to compound.
in a world still dominated by extraction that orientation may itself become one of the rarest assets. Can you talk about that because I think it's actually a really important idea and I feel like part of what happened to me is as I grew up I sort of saw there was one way of doing things and you're like whoa it's just all this really Darwinian stuff and I'm just going to lose if I'm not really sharp elbow. And then you know I think what's kind of heartening is sort of to see oh no actually there's this other.
approach that's not extractive and that's not about you know, dominate and kill. Your listeners are going to be like, how did he see two, two fifty GTOs? But just to cure the curiosity, one of the most important restoration shops in the world for these vintage cars is Paul Russell. And he happens to have his shop about five minutes from our office. So once in a while, I just see these and
incredible vehicles drive by. And it was one day they were prepping two of the most valuable cars in the world to go out for an event in California. So I did see two Ferrari GTOs go by and even Nick Sleep's written about these in his Nomad letters. So I was like seeing two unicorns in the same day, two different unicorns. But yeah, scarcity
I'm so happy you're reading these things, by the way, because it's hard to articulate when they're in real time. Yeah, that does sum it up. These relationships that were built in there, when you were reading that, I was thinking of the Mendelssohn's of Haika. It's a family I've had into the classroom every year for probably the last 12 years. Larry Mendelssohn.
just passed away, we dedicated our semester to him. But here's this aerospace company, but it's every member of the family's involved, the way they treat their employees, the way they interact with the world. And for that, they get this premium evaluation, this premium experience. They're just doing the right thing, and they're doing it consistently. And it's one of my favorite examples to show the students because they're just like, wow, look at how success can look.
when you behave well and you act with that kind of integrity over a long period of time. So you realize that success can be, you can win without this extractive short-termism that might seem like it's the fastest way. And that's one of the principles that we really try to just show by example versus by words. Yeah.
Before I let you go, Chris, I wanted to ask you if I may, I know I'm exhausting your patience, but I wanted to ask you about two more things, one of which may be a little downbeat, but which I think is important, and one less is also important, but more cheering. I wanted to ask you a little bit, if I may, about your first wife, Lynn Begg, who passed away in February at the age of 53. You and I had talked about it, and I very kindly sent me her obituary. It's such an amazing story. She's the mother of your daughter Caroline.
So even though you had divorced, she is such an important part of your life because you both very actively evolved in raising a kid together and you had married young. And I wonder if you could just talk a little bit about what you learned from her partly because she had this extraordinary story that I read about in the obituary of three different people had given her kidneys over the years, starting I think when she was at the University of New Hampshire.
And so there's something sort of so amazing about about human nature and also about the fact that she had to live with this life threatening disease for almost half a century. And so I'm wondering when you know you must have thought a lot about her life and your time together and what you know what we what we can learn from her and how she handled what she went through. He was just extraordinary in her distant her life and her example of.
dealing with hardship and disease for the whole kidney disease for a whole life. But to do it in a way that was such such composure and never wanted sympathy at all. So, yeah, she's a... We miss her a lot. Yeah, I was really struck there was a line in the obituary where it said, Lynn was a warrior battling kidney disease since the age of five and yet living a vibrant full life filled with love and laughter. I'm always like so impressed with that because
I have such a capacity for whining when things are good. When you look at someone, always think about how I snatched defeat from the jewels of victory by complaining about things. And when you look at someone who, I think she could be so active in terms of her interests, her sports, sailing all of these things while having that condition. There's only kind of stunning about it, right? Yeah.
Now, she's a wonderful example of all the things that we've talked about today and just resilience and just living, doing the great work really. Yeah, I also thought they were saying really lovely. I'm sure you would have noticed this and I'm sorry to put you through talking about this. But when you were writing to me about going to the burial and I was looking back and I'm like, wait, it was at a church called Our Lady of Good Voyage Church? I mean, like giving you a love of
of boats and surfing and sailing you know and her love of so much such an amazing thing that the just the name of that all lady of good voyage church. Such a beautiful church and it's in the great town of Gloucester, Massachusetts which is the place that she lived in for the last 10 years and it's such a beautiful church because it was the church that a lot of these these fishermen would you know when they passed away the services would be there and.
And just how much of the ocean is surrounded by that town and both the highs and lows of living in Gloucester. So it was a beautiful service, very fitting celebration of her life. Yeah. Anyway, I hope you don't mind. I wanted to mention that because I think it's always good to sort of honor the memory of people who have played an important or be a complicated role in our lives.
And on a sort of mortuary note, like, I wanted to ask you about another experience with your son with the beautiful name River, because we have been texting back earlier in the year. And you, you texted me and you said, I went to surf today. It was a full moon and I get to the beach and it was dark and expected. Then I realized I was experiencing a full lunar eclipse in totality at that very moment, 430 a.m. or 333 a.m. Eastern Standard Time.
And I wonder if you could talk about that experience because it sounds like such an unbelievable experience and such an amazing thing to share with a young kid. It was so cool. Yeah, one of the things that we set our monthly calendars around is surfing the full moon. And, you know, the morning of the full moon, it's, you know, you get out there at 430 and usually have about 45 minutes prior to the sun kind of surfacing.
you get this moment that the ocean texture feels like silk. There's some so alive to surfing with the moon coming into the ocean just at the time that the sun is lifting up. You get these both experiences at the same time. My son, who's finally just emerged into going from seven years old surfing white water to now being out the back surfing real waves. It was his first full moon surf.
we get down to the beach and we're like, did I miscalculate? I could have sworn this is supposed to be a full moon. Where's the moon? And it was like the universe like laughing at us in such a beautiful way. And I'm like, oh my goodness, this is the lunar eclipse. And it wasn't just, oh, it was at the exact moment of the eclipse. It was completely blocked out. It was so extraordinary.
And it got to experience it with the river and we still paddled out and got to surf. It was much darker than we normally would have had it. It's really lovely. You said to me that you went back to get River so he could see it. We sat there on the beach together until the sun rose and I texted you back and said, I wonder if River will remember sitting with you on that beach till sunrise for the rest of his life. I said, that's an A1 piece of parenting. And you wrote back, thank you. I know I will.
And I just, for me it was very powerful because it was like this sort of like, here we are sort of in my case writing about it and in your case practicing this craft that's all about building wealth. And it's like that, you know, in a way like what greater sense of wealth could you have at that than that moment with your boy on the beach, you know, watching, watching that. It's been such a gift to see him experience nature at this level.
having learned how important it is and him experiencing it as part of the texture of his life. You know, these experiences with being here in Costa Rica or and having that connection, it's really cool to see. It's really cool to see. And then we have our youngest one who's now one and a half, 17 months now, starting to wake up to the same, the same newness of life.
And as I think we discussed last time, named Piper. After that acronym of persistent, persistent incremental progress, eternally repeated, if I remember rightly. You got it. So I also loved your idea that kids in a sense are edge nodes. Can you just explain that to sort of dot the eyes and cross the T's? Because in a way, it kind of, it completes this picture of everything being a graph. It does. Yeah.
I think having close contact with where learning happens is very special. And with a child and seeing learning through the eyes of a child, the proximity to the contact of their experience with novelty. Learning, I dropped my son off at Skateboard Camp today and he's trying to figure this new thing out.
proximity to learning is that edge note experience, right? It's like, I guess that's what gets me excited about going in the classroom every year or seeing it through the eyes of a 17 month old. And the way that a 17 month learns is by crying, right? His idea of reality has just been completely obliterated and he breaks out in tears and that's a learning experience, right? Maybe some of us, we continue to learn through tears and it's, uh, yes, that proximity to the
where reality and learning interface is a gift. And we see it through our children. We see it through students. I just had a, my good friend Paul Buser was here for a week with his daughter, Lily. And she's 17. And she's, she did an internship this week with us. It was so fun because she's in this threshold moment of writing her college essays. And so we're introducing her to some of these investments. And you could see her eyes are just like, I didn't know this world
prior, it was such a kind of like a moment to see it, you know. And so I think each stage in life, we have these. And the more we have them, the better the better life is, I think. Yeah, you always leave me with a sense of everything being kind of an adventure and I should be optimistic because there's cool stuff coming. So thank you because it's always such a delight chatting with you. And I always just feel like after we talk, I'm like, I'm really glad you're in my life.
I really am. And so I'm grateful to have you as a friend and I've learned a lot from you over the years. And I should really give credit to Josh Tarasoff who introduced us and knew that this would be a relationship worth forging. And I think from the moment I met you, I was like, this is someone I want in my life. So thank you, Chris. Well, William, you've given so much to my life and I've loved spending time with you and you're such a student.
I love everything you're doing and a little shout out to Josh too. Josh is a dear, dear friend. I'm so happy he introduced us. Ah, a lovely man. All right. Well, thanks so much and hopefully I'll see you again very soon. Sounds great. Thanks, William. Thanks. Thanks for listening to TIP. Follow Richard, Wiser, Happier on your favorite podcast app and visit theinvestorspodcast.com for show notes and educational resources.
This podcast is for informational and entertainment purposes only and does not provide financial, investment, tax or legal advice. The content is impersonal and does not consider your objectives, financial situation or needs. Investing involves risk including possible loss of principal and past performance is not a guarantee of future results. Listeners should do their own research and consult a qualified professional before making any financial decisions. Nothing on this show is a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell any security or other financial product. Hosts, guests,
and the Investors' Podcast Network may hold positions in securities discussed and may change those positions at any time without notice. References to any third-party products, services, or advertisers do not constitute endorsements, and the Investors' Podcast Network is not responsible for any claims made by them. Copyright by the Investors' Podcast Network. All rights reserved.